A Guide to the Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files, 1939-1940
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files 1939-1940
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.491, IV
This collection consists of 7,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Scope and Content Information
These files constitute the major record series generated by the president of the University of Virginia. The records consist chiefly of correspondence, but also include reports, minutes, clippings, memoranda, and related papers concerning all areas of business of the president's office.
Contents List
- General Files, 1939-1940
  - "A" Miscellaneous (1 of 2) reference to Akerman--Forestry trip to Europe, Conditions in Germany poor, in Switzerland good; A.B.C.--advice to close between 12 midnight and 5 a.m.; Alderman, Mrs.--Keck about bust and personal correspondence 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - "A" Miscellaneous (2 of 2) reference to A.A.U.W.--will inhabitants of area give homes to British children 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Council reference to Carliner Case 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Aeronautics reference to UVa. Airport--development of an airfield 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Alderman, Life of--Dumas Malone--agreement and conditions of writing 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--General Correspondence 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Investments 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Meeting 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Presidents Contingent Fund 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Fund--Class Managers Bulletin 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Fund--Council 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Office 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - American Council on Education: Educational Associations Questionnaire 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Ancient Languages 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Art and Architecture--Campbell Correspondence 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Articles re: University of Virginia reference to Wranek and other publications 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Association of American Colleges reference to notice of meetings, agenda 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Association of American Universities reference to notice of meetings, agenda 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Astronomy 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Athletics 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - "B" Miscellaneous reference to Bryan, John Stewart--correspondence between 2 college Presidents; Buchanan, Annabel--Folk songs and music; Byrd, Harry F.--series of formal notes 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Biology--Blandy Farm 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Biology--Mountain Lake 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Biology--general 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Bayly Art Museum 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Budget 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--The Cellar 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Cemetery 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Chemistry Building 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Colonnade Club 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Commons 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Electricity, X-Rays 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Faculty Apartments reference to Mrs. Lambeth, Mr. Nelson 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Faculty Housing 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Flying Field 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Fraternities reference to Sigma Nu 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Fuel 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--General 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Gymnasium 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Neuro-Psychiatric area; Interns' Quarters; Nurses Home 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Insurance 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Intern's Quarters 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Library 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Madison Hall 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Monroe Hall 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Observatory; Water Tank 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Roads 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Rotunda and Lawns 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Scott Stadium 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Speech Buildings reference to chairs 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Bursar's Office 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Bursar--Rotunda Restoration reference to plans, costs 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - "C" Miscellaneous reference to Commission on County Government--tentative report; Corbett, Hames--Mixture of Board of Visitors letters and personal correspondence; Crenshaw, Lewis-- Recommendation that R. H. Wilson be elected to French Legion of Honor 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Carnegie Corporation 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Chemistry Department 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Church Society for College Work reference to College Topics; Easter Week 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Commerce and Business Administration 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Committee of Deans reference to discusses duplication of efforts in higher education in Virginia 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Convocations 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - "D" Miscellaneous reference to Daniels, Josephus--wants copy of speech made in Paris on Jefferson; Davis, Arthur Kyle--Folklore Society to meet here 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Dean Ferguson reference to papers re: Committee on Academic Legislation 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Dean Lewis reference to academic standing of first-year men 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - DuPont Trust 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - "E" Miscellaneous reference to Echols, A.B.--Donation to Quarterly Review 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Education 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Emergency Committee on Displaced Persons 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Engineering 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - English--Kent School 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Extension Division reference to report of occupational counseling 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - "F" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Finals reference to Programs; list for receptions 1939-1940 (Box 6)
    File includes correspondence concerning Franklin D. Roosevelt, who delivered the famous "hand that held the dagger" speech at Finals. The file does not include a copy of the text of the speech.
  - Forestry 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Forestry reference to Seward Forest 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Form Letters 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Founder's Day reference to Sumner Wells, speaker; Benes visit 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - "G" Miscellaneous reference to Garnett, Christopher--correspondence; Gooch, Robert K.--Questions re: tenure 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - General Education Board reference to Physics Department; Blandy Farm; Rural Social Economics Department 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Geological Survey 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Geology 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - German 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Governor's Office (1 of 3) 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Governor's Office (2 of 3) reference to Long-Term Program for State Colleges and Universities; Analysis of Building Program; Seward Forest; First question re: black law; Eleanor Roosevelt 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Governor's Office (3 of 3) 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Graduate Dept. 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - "H" Miscellaneous reference to Hall, Sidney--education in Virginia; Hampton Institute--publishing of "Negro in Virginia," inauguration of Dr. McLean 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Hospital--Addition 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Hospital--UVa.--Ward Patient Statistics 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - "I" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Insurance 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Interracial Cooperation Commission 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - Invitations to be represented (1939) 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - Invitations to be represented (1940) 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - Institute of Public Affairs 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - "J" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - "K" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - "L" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - Law Department reference to Law Library--needs, costs; John Bassett Moore School of International Law; Tenure; N.C. College for Negroes 1939-1940 (Box 9)
  - Lectures 1939-1940 (Box 9)
  - Legal Papers reference to W. A. Perkins, attorney 1939-1940 (Box 9)
  - Legislative Program 1939 1939-1940 (Box 9)
  - Legislative Program 1940 1939-1940 (Box 9)
  - Library--Alderman reference to incidental correspondence 1939-1940 (Box 10)
  - Library--McGregor Library reference to includes Library Committee Minutes 1939-1940 (Box 10)
  - "M" Miscellaneous reference to McIntire, Paul G.--letters concerning Newcomb's health; approval of Life of President Alderman1939-1940 (Box 10)
  - Madison Hall 1939-1940 (Box 10)
  - Mathematics 1939-1940 (Box 10)
  - McIntire Fund 1939-1940 (Box 10)
  - Medical Department (1 of 2) 1939-1940 (Box 10)
  - Medical Department (2 of 2) reference to Survey of Joint Health departments; Drash's plan for surgery in different parts of the state 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - Medical Department--Hospital reference to Dr. Lentz 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - Medical Department--Student Health Service 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - Mellon Fund 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - Music reference to plans for reorganization of the department 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - "N" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - National Association of State Universities 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - National Youth Administration reference to report on occupational counseling 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - Naval ROTC--curriculum 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - Negro Admissions--lists 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - "O" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - "P" Miscellaneous reference to Porterfield, Robert--Conference at Barter Theater 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Patents Committee 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Personnel 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Phi Beta Kappa 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Philosophy 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Physical Education 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Physics 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Political Science 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Prospective Donors 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Psychology 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Public Administration 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Public Speaking 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - "Q" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Questionnaires 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - "R" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Recommendations 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Religion 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Rhodes Scholars reference to lists 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Romance Languages 1939-1940 (Box 12)
  - Rural Social Economics (1 of 2) 1939-1940 (Box 13)
  - Rural Social Economics (2 of 2) reference to correspondence with staff; reports of Wilson Gee 1939-1940 (Box 13)
  - "S" Miscellaneous (1 of 2) reference to Sigma Xi chapter list; prizes, programs 1939-1940 (Box 13)
  - "S" Miscellaneous (2 of 2) reference to Stettinius letters--to and from Newcomb 1939-1940 (Box 13)
  - Separated State Universities 1939-1940 (Box 13)
  - Sociology 1939-1940 (Box 13)
  - Southern University Conference 1939-1940 (Box 13)
  - State Supported Institutions--Association of Presidents (1 of 2) 1939-1940 (Box 13)
  - State Supported Institutions--Association of Presidents (2 of 2) 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - Statistics 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - Student Senate--Questionnaire on Topics 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - Sullivan Foundation Award 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - Summer Session reference to courses re: comparison with other schools 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - "T" Miscellaneous reference to Tucker, Bishop Beverly--Board of Visitors; Taylor, Henry J.--correspondence 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - "U" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - "V" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - Visitors--General Correspondence reference to portrait of Dr. Lambeth; Theta Chi house 1939-1940 (Box 14)
  - Visitors--Finance Committee 1939-1940 (Box 15)
  - Visitors--meetings 1939-1940 (Box 15)
  - Visitors--Robert B. Tunstall 1939-1940 (Box 15)
  - "W" Miscellaneous reference to Watson, T.L.--UVa. acceptance of portrait; Weddell, Alexander--fellowship at University of Salamanca; Williams, Carrington--report of Committee of Publicity 1939-1940 (Box 15)
  - White, William H.--Foundation Lectures 1939-1940 (Box 15)
  - Woodrow Wilson Birthplace Foundation 1939-1940 (Box 15)
  - W.P.A. 1939-1940 (Box 15)
  - "X-Y-Z" Miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 15)